Well, all right. It's time to kick off
Unifi with an absolute banger. Because,
in case you don't know, America's
destiny ain't going to manifest itself
in this period. That's right. It's time
to set up the pieces that are going to
lead us into the Civil War. And it
begins with Westward expansion. So, if
you're ready to get them brain cows
milked, let's get to it. Okay, so the
time period for this unit is 1844 to
1877. And 1844 is significant because it
marked the election of President James
K. Pulk. Now, I'll talk more about him
in the next video, but for now, you just
need to know that Pulk's whole campaign
was an appeal to US expansion into the
West. And that's the major theme of this
unit because it's going to cause all
kinds of problems that the US, as it
turned out, could only solve through a
great cataclysm of violence known as the
Civil War. But listen, I need to begin
by telling you that westward migration
has always been written deep in the code
of Americans DNA, even since the
colonial period. Now, remember that the
British imposition of the proclamation
line of 1763 prevented American
colonists from migrating west into the
Ohio River Valley, which, you know, big
mistake. Yeah, it turned out that set
off a firestorm of colonial grievances
that led to the American Revolution. And
that's why Thomas Jefferson wrote in the
Declaration of Independence, "George
didn't let us go west up, so he about to
get messed up." I mean, that line didn't
make it into the final draft, but you
know, the spirit was there. Anyway,
after the Revolution, Americans got all
that territory for themselves and got
their migration on quick, fast, and in a
hurry. Then in 1803, the Louisiana
purchased double the size of the United
States and provided millions of acres of
land for yman farmers to migrate and
establish their homesteads. And westward
migration was especially important to
southern cotton farmers who were always
hungry for fresh soil on account of
their cotton crops sucked all the
nutrients from the ground. And that
meant that they always needed more
acreage to keep up with the fantastic
demand for export in domestic and
international markets. All of which of
course was facilitated by the market
revolution that we talked all about in
the last unit. Okay. Of equal
importance, the west served as a kind of
social safety net as well. Remember all
the way back to the debates over the
ratification of the constitution. Now,
one of the biggest gripes of the
anti-federalist was that a nation as big
as the United States, both in population
and land mass, would be too unwieldy for
a central government to effectively
manage. But Federalists argued back that
whatever problem sprang up in the most
populated places, they would always have
a ready solution, namely westward
migration. It was seen as a kind of
pressure release valve for the tensions
that built up in the most populated
areas of the country. So all that to
say, the western frontier always held
something of a mythological quality for
Americans. And in many ways, the
possibility of westward migration had
always been a key ingredient in the
American identity. However, in this
period, the push for westward migration
reached its absolute height. And why is
that says you? Well, says I. We can
break it down into two categories.
Ideological reasons and practical
reasons for migration. Before we get to
those reasons, let me just say that if
you believe your destiny is to get an A
in this class and a five on your exam in
May, then I got just the thing to help
you manifest it. It's my A pushheimler
review guide and it's got everything you
need to study for your exams as fast as
possible. It's got whole unit review
videos that are not here on YouTube,
practice questions, fulllength practice
exams, and a sassy Himler bot that's
going to answer any of your questions.
So, you know, if that's something you're
into, check that link in the
description. Okay, so first, let's
consider the ideological reason
Americans got their westward expansion
on during this period. And for that,
it's time to talk about manifest
destiny. So, this term was popularized
by a conservative newspaper editor named
John O Sullivan. Essentially, it was the
nationalistic idea that God had blessed
the United States and given it a mission
to spread itself over the whole of the
North American continent from sea to
shining sea. And hey, that sounds nice.
But as we're going to see, this ideology
of manifest destiny is going to cause
two wars. The MexicanAmerican War and
the Civil War. And manifest destiny is
going to cause endless conflict and
violence with American Indians living in
those western territories. So, my dear O
Sullivan, do you per chance have any
evidence that the Almighty has indeed
tasked the United States with this
mission? Well, as it turns out, he does
have some evidence, and I'll let him say
it in his own words. And that claim is
by the right of our manifest destiny to
overspread and to possess the whole of
the continent which providence has given
us for the development of the great
experiment of liberty and federated
self-government entrusted to us. Okay,
did you hear it? Like the reason why the
United States has been tasked by God to
claim the whole North American continent
is because they are the ones with
liberty and self-government. Okay, so
according to manifest destiny, American
freedom and its forms of government are
so superior to any institutions found in
the West that it's worth whatever blood
and money it cost to spread it as far as
the Pacific Ocean. And Americans were
increasingly convinced that it was
necessary to aggressively acquire more
indigenous land because they were seen
as a barrier to progress. Not to
mention, many Americans believe that
American Indians didn't use their land
in the proper manner to begin with. And
so ultimately with that kind of
thinking, American expansion west would
be kind of like a favor to the backwards
people who were already living there.
Okay, so now let's consider the
practical reasons for the big push for
westward migration during this period.
And there are no less than four that you
need to know. First, Americans migrated
westward to access natural and mineral
resources and to find new economic
opportunities. And the territories that
would provide such opportunities were
Texas, California, and Oregon. Now,
Texas would become a US state right at
the beginning of this period, namely
1845. And that act would ultimately set
off a war between the US and Mexico. And
my next video is going to be all about
that. But for now, all you really need
to know is that the vast plains of Texas
were highly desirable for southern
planters who needed new soil. and the
fact that they brought slavery with them
into Texas would cause its own problem.
Okay. Second, the Oregon territory was
highly desirable for its fertile soil as
well. Now, as a result of a treaty
signed in 1818, this massive swath of
land was jointly occupied by the US and
Great Britain. But during this period,
the Americans manifested their destiny
all over this territory by migrating and
settling there in far greater numbers
than did the British. And the whole
reason American migrants were crazy to
move there is because news of the
magnificently fertile soil in the
Willilt Valley reached the east along
with stories of farmers who had already
met success in planting. And so that
sparked what became known as Oregon
fever and attracted around 350,000
American settlers by 1860 who traveled
along the famed Oregon Trail. And
therefore claiming Oregon for the US
became a central tenant in James K.
Pulk's campaign platform. The slogan was
5440 or fight and referred to the
northern border of the Oregon territory
way up in Canada and suggested that the
US was willing to go to war with Britain
yet again if they couldn't get their
greedy hands on that juicy Oregon soil.
And then the third territory Americans
desired for economic opportunity was
California. Now, for the first half of
the 19th century, California, which was
Mexican territory, attracted relatively
few Americans. But in 1848, gold was
discovered in them bar hills, and thus
began a massive migration to the region
known as the California Gold Rush. And
in only a few years, the sheer numbers
of American migrants who occupied
settlements in Mexican California seemed
to communicate that like Texas,
California too would soon be in the
grasp of the expansion-minded United
States. Okay. Now, let's move on to the
second practical reason for the flurry
of westward expansion during this
period, and that was new government
policies encouraging settlement of the
West. This effort had deep roots in the
old Jeffersonian vision of the United
States as an empire of liberty for the
yman farmer. So first in 1841, Congress
passed the preeemption act which granted
squatters the right to buy up to 160
acres in the western federal territories
before they went up for sale publicly.
Now a squatter by definition was
somebody who established a homestead on
a piece of land which they did not own.
So this law granted squatters the right
to purchase the land on which they lived
at a very low price on the condition
that they would live there and improve
the land for at least 5 years. And so
the passage of this law led to a big
wave of migrants who would now be able
to own a parcel of land at a price that
many of them could now afford. In fact,
most of the Nebraska and Kansas
territories were organized and settled
as a result of this provision from the
federal government. And then things got
even wilder in 1862 when Congress passed
the Homestead Act. Now, at this point,
the Civil War had already begun and that
meant that the southern states had
seceded from the Union. And now that all
southern representatives had departed
Congress to form their own Confederate
legislature, the federal government
seized the opportunity to weaken future
southern claims in the West, especially
their desire to spread slavery across
the continent. Dirty move, but hey,
respect. So, the Homestead Act was very
similar to the Preeemption Act in that
it offered Americans 160 acres in
western federal territory on the
condition that they lived there and
improved the land for at least 5 years.
But the big difference is that under the
Homestead Act, the land was free. Excuse
me. Did you just say that the federal
government was giving away 160acre plots
to Americans for free? That is indeed
what I said. And so it's not hard to
imagine that farmers migrated west by
the metric buttload at this offer. And
as a result, most of the remaining
western territory of the United States
was organized and settled by 1890, at
which point the frontier was declared
closed. Now, don't get the idea that
when Americans got to their plots in all
this western territory that they found a
pristine, vacant tract of land on which
nothing but happy deer and contented
squirrels frolked their days away. No,
you always have to remember that
Americans migrating west is going to
cause conflict with the people already
living there, namely various groups of
American Indians. Like in many cases,
land west of the Mississippi River was
designated by a federal treaty as Indian
territory. But the congressional
policies that I just mentioned that
encouraged US migration unilaterally
broke those treaties and further
displaced American Indians living in the
west. Now, some groups like the
Comanches living in southern Texas
retaliated violently to westward
migration, but eventually all such
indigenous resistance was conquered by
the spreading empire of the United
States. Okay. Now, the third practical
reason for westward expansion during
this period was a desire for religious
refuge. And the poster boys and girls
for this were, of course, the Mormons.
So, after their founder, Joseph Smith,
was murdered in Illinois, Mormons set
their sights on migrating to the Utah
territory in order to practice their
religion without, you know, getting
murdered. Therefore, in 1847, they
launched a massive exodus led by Smith's
successor, Brigham Young, traveling
thousands of miles west and settling
near the Great Salt Lake in Utah, which
at that point was still Mexican
territory. In fact, over the course of
only a few years, something like 16,000
Mormon migrants had settled in Utah. And
finally, the fourth practical reason
Americans had for westward expansion
during this period was a growing
interest in trade with Asian countries.
Now, US trade with China had declined
around the middle of the 19th century.
And so, the US government turned to
Japan. And here's where I tell you that
Japan had been closed to trade with
foreigners for about 200 years by this
point on account of they really didn't
like Westerners. So, the US took
cautious, respectful, diplomatic steps
to persuade Japan to open their ports.
Wouldn't [laughter] it be hilarious if
that's what they did? No. In 1854,
Commodore Matthew Perry arrived at
Japanese ports with a fleet of warships,
threatening war if Japan did not agree
to open trade with the United States.
And ultimately, Japan agreed to the
terms of the American tantrum. And as a
result, two ports were open to limited
trade with the United States. Okay,
click here to keep watching my other
videos for unit 5, and click here to
grab my Himler review guide, which is
going to help you get an A in your class
and a five on your exam in May. And I'm
glad you came around, and I'll catch you
on the flip-flop. I'm lur out.